No and welcome back. Let us see the wiener filter in action
大家好 欢迎回到我们的课程 我们将再次利用MATLAB
once again using MATHLAB. As we have done before we start by
来演示维纳滤波器 (wiener filter) 的例子 和之前一样 我们先载入一幅图像
loading an image. This is the same image we have seen
这个图像我们以前看到过
before, this Saturn image, remember that was a color image.
这个土星 (Saturn) 的图像 它是个彩色图像
So we're going to transform it into black and white image, the same operation as we
所以我们要将它转换成黑白图像 这个操作之前也用到过
did before. Then we're going to add Gaussian noise,
然后我们给图像加上高斯噪声 (Gaussian noise)
as we see here, we have seen this before when we were showing the different types
这个步骤在这里 之前演示不同类型的噪声时 我们也用到了这个命令
of noise and we see here the variance. Now, are go and apply the wiener filter.
这个参数是噪声的方差 现在 我们要用到维纳滤波器了
This is the operation that applies the wiener filter to this image that we have
在MATLAB中 这个命令能够调用维纳滤波器
just basically created by adding Gaussian noise.
我们将用它来处理这个叠加了高斯噪声的图像
Now before I show you the result of the Wiener filter I want to compare that with
在展示维纳滤波器的处理结果之前 我想把它和另外一个滤波器做比较
a different filter. Basically, I want to compare it with a
事实上 我想把它和均值滤波器做比较
local averaging. For that I'm creating a disk of radius
我将用半径为10的圆形区域
ten and then basically filtering the noise image with that disk.
对噪声图像进行滤波
This is basically, this operation is basically computing the
这个命令用到了
local average, weka window of radius ten.
半径为10的圆形区域来计算局部均值
Don't worry about this, this is just a, what, is telling MATHLAB
别担心这个参数 这只是告诉MATLAB
what to do at the boundary conditions. So basically, we're going to have, the
在边界条件下如何进行处理 所以 我们将会看到
original image, we're going to have the noisy image, we're going to have the
原始图像 噪声图像
blurry image, local averaging, and we're going to have the result of Wiener
均值滤波器处理后的模糊图像 还有维纳滤波器处理后的图像
filtering. So let's see the results.
那么 我们来看看这些结果
Once again we're loading all the images. And this will help us to see how nice
我们将载入所有图像 这将有助于看到
wiener filtering can work. we see again the original image, that we
维纳滤波器是多么有效 我们又看到了先前的原始图像
have seen in the past. This is the noisy image.
这个是叠加了噪声的图像
This is the result of Wiener filtering. And this is the result of blurring, or
这个是维纳滤波器的处理结果 这个是均值滤波器的处理结果
local averaging. So see how nicely Wiener filtering has
可以看到维纳滤波器修复后的结果
been able to recover. Restore a lot of the original image,
相当得不错 它利用这个噪声图像
starting from this noisy image. And it has done a much better job than
很好地还原了原始图像 而且它比均值滤波器做得更好
the local averaging. Let me move the image closer, and we can
我把两幅图像放近些 这样我们就能够
see the difference. This is clearly a much sharper image than
看到两者的差异 这幅图像明显
what we obtained knowing basically, doing the local averaging.
比用均值滤波器得到的结果更加清晰
So wiener as we see can do a fantastic job when we provide some information.
所以 当我们向维纳滤波器提供一些信息时 它的处理结果会很好
And in this case, actually, the wiener is estimating the information.
在这种情况下 维纳滤波器会评估它得到的信息
So this is the, basically the implementation that we saw
我们在前一个视频的最后看到过这个实现方式
at the end of the previous video, the simplest implementation of the wiener
它是实现维纳滤波器最简单的方式
filtering and still able to do a great job in restoring the image, starting from
但是仍然能够利用噪声图像 很好地修复出原始图像
this noisy image. Then we once again, this was the
我们再看一下这些图像
original, the noisy of course the wiener filter doesn't know this original images
这是原始图像 这是噪声图像 当然 维纳滤波器并不知道这个原始图像
starts from this noisy image and still operating that blurry version of it,
它利用噪声图像修复出相当清晰的图像
creates a really sharp version. So it's doing a really, really good job.
而不是模糊的图像 所以它修复得相当棒
And we can see much better than the local averaging that blurs.
我们可以看到 这比用均值滤波器产生的模糊图像好很多
So by this we conclude that themma on the wiener victory.
这样我们就结束了对维纳滤波器的演示
Thank you very much.
非常感谢